Hello, what are the main financial
and operational risks in agriculture?
Such as droughts, lack of irrigation,
or crop failure, that small farmers face?
Main problems are legal framework,
because Moldova has started
30 years ago a land reform
which is not finished.
So many farmers are not secure
what fields they can use.
First, there is also a main obstacle
for investors, by the way.
And the second problem, especially
for small farmers:
a lack of professional education
and also a lack of financial literacy.
Have there been cases in your practice
when financial support
or loans to agriculture enterprises
did not pay off?
Or issues arose with repayment
because farmers mismanaged their budgets?
Yes, of course,
it is a logical effect.
If you lack professional know-how
and knowledge,
then you do the wrong things.
You apply the wrong fertilizers,
the wrong machinery.
So this happens quite often.
We are developing a platform where
artificial intelligence will process data
from field sensors and predict
irrigation needs
based on real weather conditions.
How much would such precision help
financial organizations and investors
reduce crop failure risks?
Such a tool can help farmers
and is also very interesting
for banks and insurance companies,
because the big complaint
of banks and financial institutions
is that farmers are not "bankable".
That means they do not provide
enough information to the banks
which refer directly to their
operational business and results.
With the help of such a tool,
they would be able to provide
better information about it.
And another problem is the insurance,
because only a small part
of the small farmers are insured.
That means if there is any hailstorm,
they often have a huge loss.
With data from sensors,
a farmer could prove the weather conditions
and prove his demands
to insurance companies.
On our platform, farmers will be able
to find educational video tutorials
from university professors
on financial planning.
How in-demand is financial literacy
education among small farmers in Moldova?
Would this help improve
their creditworthiness?
Professional know-how and
financial literacy is really needed,
and farmers like to get know-how
about these topics.
Our platform plans to feature
a separate information block
with real testing results
of technologies on pilot farms.
How much will this help
financial structures and investors
direct funds only
toward proven solutions?
Well, to spread best practices
is always good,
but it would be not enough
just to present the best results.
You should also present the way
how you can achieve these good results.
The target group for this
I see mainly in local farmers,
not that much in investors,
because the investors usually
do not need that much tips
like the local farmers.
Okay, thank you so much.